okay welcome back to the devil debates
with an angel hi new people yeah so this
is a text that was written in 1500s and
it's a very famous in Tibet and it's an
argument within one person's mind
between their good side and the bad side
the good side specifically is looking at
the world in a way which is correct and
the bad side is looking at the way the
world in a way which is not correct and
just to make it simple the correct way
to look at the world or how we
understand the world is that as you
interact with other people you plant
seeds in your mind if you do nice things
to other people you plant good seeds in
your mind if you do bad things to other
people you get bad seeds in your mind
and then your reality is flowing from
these seeds small pictures are flowing
out of those seeds those seeds are
called karma and then your life the
people you meet the guide that just ran
me over in the traffic it took me a lot
of it took me about ten minutes to
figure out it came from me you know like
I couldn't remember for the first ten
minutes you know so the idea is that if
you keep aware that people who run you
off the road are coming from you you
won't get so angry at them you'll just
try to drive better and then you won't
see them again that's how to get rid of
them so and then the devil in this case
is trying to tell you no no he's not
your fault he was just driving on the
same road he's a I'm not supposed to say
bad words he's just an [__] and he's
running you off the road you know and
he's not your fault is his fault you
know while talking and then the angel
would say no no everything you see is
coming from you good things bad things
are coming from me okay so that's the
basic argument that's going on in
one person's mind in this text which is
about 500 years old and the author is
the first pension Lama who is very
famous and so we're gonna start where we
left off yesterday I'm still doing a
review of the last 10 sessions that
started in 2010 right and if we finished
tonight pretty far we will be 10% done
with the text okay and I hope one day I
think it's one of the greatest spiritual
books ever written I think it's like a
Rumi or or something like that and I
think if you know if we can get through
it I've translated it literally and then
somebody should take it and make it
poetic you know so here we go we talked
about the parts at the hall so one of
the proofs of emptiness the basic
meaning of emptiness is not that there's
nothing exist it's not that everything
is a black hole it's not that everything
in this illusion it's not that you
shouldn't think about anything it's not
that you should watch thoughts go
through your mind none of those is
emptiness because they don't help you
succeed okay if you really understand
Antonis you should be a very successful
person because what understanding
emptiness means the guy who ran me off
the road who wasn't my fault
okay the guy who ran me off the road who
wasn't my fault okay who was coming from
his own son doesn't exist never did
exist couldn't exist will exist okay
this is cut now yeah couldn't exist okay
I'll say it again a guy who's not coming
from me who ran me off the road this
evening doesn't exist you see what I
mean and his non-existence is called
emptiness in Buddhism okay
so the fact that there's nobody to blame
except yourself is called emptiness and
that's the real meaning of emptiness
every other thing every other thing you
ever heard about emptiness is completely
wrong
probably the absence of that is also
emptiness all right so there are many
many ways to prove emptiness and angel
in the mind is trying he's offered to
the devil that she will share some of
those proofs of emptiness with him okay
and we're picking up at parts and holes
we did parts and holes already with your
body or with a car okay and the classic
argument and by the way this argument
has been misunderstood by hundreds and
thousands of people in the last two
thousand years so you go to many many
Buddhist talks even by big Lamas and you
will hear ridiculous things okay so
here's the correct one and it's easy and
it's clear and you can use it for your
life so you know either you are all of
your parts together or you are one of
your parts okay and last night we talked
about your foot you know am i my foot no
that part's easy okay in my my legs arms
torso head all put together no not yet
okay why there's always one final piece
that you have to add to make the whole
and that's the state of mind
which organizes the pieces into a whole
you see what I mean without that state
of mind you can't function that's what
happens to people Alzheimer's okay John
and me are on the edge of it right they
forget how to glue pieces together and
actually karma is wearing out in their
life karma is wearing out they they
can't piece together things anymore and
that's just karma you see and that's a
temporary ability your mind is also
flowing
from karma in your mind and someday the
karma will end and you will die in
between here and there the mind starts
to lose its energy like any tree for
example as it gets older and then you
you you can't paste things together so
the ability to paste things together
into objects is the final piece of every
composite thing okay including you all
right like this guy who ran me off the
road he had a car he had arms he had
legs he had head I don't know but I put
it together you see and someone else
riding next to me would have said oh you
know he's the only person driving well
here you should speed up getting my home
you know you see what I mean so that's
the emptiness of the guy who ran me off
the road until seats open in my mind
from doing dangerous things in my life
you know until I stopped those seats I
will continue to see people like that
because they're coming from me
okay that's the emptiness of my body
that's the parts and holes of my body
and where the pension llama goes from
here he goes to the mental parts and
home okay of your Martin okay so is your
mind made of pieces yes in Buddhist
psychology 51 pieces of your mind you
know like attention or jealousy or
memory and Buddhist psychology has two
different presentations and and there's
a certain amount of functions in your
mind okay is any one of those Daniels
mind is Daniels attention Daniel's mine
no well that's just one part you see but
what about all the parts together all
the memories all the attention all the
intelligence all the other things all
together are they Daniels money not yet
okay and usually when we study the
emptiness of the mind we talk about the
mind stream okay we don't talk about the
mind in one moment we talk about the
Daniels mind since he got up this
morning
up to now okay so that's been so many
hours right I'm not asking what time you
got up but let's say he got up it's 8
o'clock was at 17 so since 8 o'clock up
to now his mind has been continuing in a
stream and that's also pieces okay
Daniel's mine at 4 o'clock Daniel's mine
at 401 Daniels mine at 402 his mind has
all of these timepieces so time has
pieces okay and how your mind glues
those pieces together is coming from
your karma okay so when you're making
out with your girlfriend when you're 17
was it at the drive-in movie I remember
one time we're at the drive-in movie we
were like 17 and the policeman came and
knocked on the door on the window and we
like why and he said we said we didn't
do anything wrong he said yeah whatever
the the movies been over for two hours
you know like get out of here close the
gate yeah and then like three hours
passes it feels like 10 minutes right
then when you go to the dentist the
opposite happens you know your friends
waiting outside they're drilling your
teeth you go out they say how long has
it been you say two three hours and then
they say no you've only been in there
for 20 minutes
you know so time can go slower or time
can go faster and that's an indication
that it's coming from you okay so the
part the pieces of your mind over time
you also glue those together and people
who get Alzheimer's or people get
amnesia they forget who they were they
don't have the Karma to put those pieces
those moments together they no longer
have the Karma to put those moments
together okay so that's what the angel
is arguing to the devil she's saying not
only is your body empty not only is your
body not all the pieces or one of the
pieces your mind is the same
okay your body and your mind are the
same okay that's her that's her proof
I'm not gonna go into the more subtle
emptiness of time because this is
something which we covered about five
years ago and hopefully these said I
should try to get to the subject tonight
I don't know okay then then the angel
says once you understand this thing
about time for example that it can go
faster or slower then you will have to
admit something slowing it down or
something speeding it up and it has
something to do with your mind okay
there must be something in your mind
that makes it go faster the dentist
clock three hours trust me okay my
lawyer would clock six hours okay yeah
actually he's a good man he's just
expensive good man okay and then she she
calls it all a single song all things
have this quality okay and I'm not gonna
spend much time on that and then they
discuss questioning the world or just
going along with it you know people say
well what geshe-la you know why talk
about all this stuff you know who cares
if my body's who cares if I put if I put
my body together or I didn't put my body
together who cares really it's all the
same anyway whether you know you're
putting together the guy on the road or
whether you don't know you're putting
together the guy on the road he still
run you off the road it doesn't really
matter just you know well the point is
since it's your mind gluing him together
if you put differences in your mind
everybody would be driving very well you
see if I can control my outside world I
can control my income I can control my
relationships I can control my house
okay I started ballet when I was what
fifty something okay you can control
your the things in your life if you
understand these things okay emptiness
is not some stupid empty philosophy it's
a practical
way to design next year and then what
you want to happen will happen okay if
you really understand karma and
emptiness you can design your future and
that's a more fun okay I'm working on
the road thing all right
okay she went to dance then she's she
says look it's good to question your
world and maybe something good will come
out of it then what did she say about
her own teaching about emptiness she
said it's empty she's telling the devil
the reason you're hearing me talk about
this emptiness is because you have the
seeds okay I'm your echo okay and
everybody you meet in the world is your
echo okay even if someone's explaining
to you about echoes that's also an echo
okay so if I always tell people if you
don't like my talk it's your fault if
you do it's me okay so she went through
the emptiness of teaching emptiness then
he says you're like a cousin who came
for a visit
I own this he keeps talking about the
mind as an apartment he wants to stay in
the apartment she wants to take it back
she's like the owner and she wants it
back okay
he says I'm part of the inner circle I'm
like Mount Meru Mount Meru is the
ancient word for Mount Everest okay
like you don't move Mount Everest okay
and he says you can push me but I'm not
going anywhere
it's like pushing del rock okay I'm not
I live here okay in the mind you come in
the mind like lightning who's you the
angel understanding the guy on the road
I will forget 2/9 again
if he meets me again okay you are here
like a blink of an eye I am the enduring
love of a mother for her child
you're the distant cousin who arrives
for an occasional visit
I'm the resident master of this mind
okay now right here
verse number 93 okay it's it's 93 verses
have passed okay we have to get to 135
just to start the class I'm sorry okay
but at this juncture after the 93rd
verse she starts criticizing wrong kinds
of meditation okay and last night I said
I prefer to call them ineffective okay
like do they make you calmer yes are
they
peaceful yes you know do you feel like a
better person afterwards yes are they
strong enough to prevent your death no
are they strong enough to prevent war in
this world no okay are they strong
enough to save your family from death no
okay so you there's basically two kinds
of meditation one is feel-good
meditation you feel like you're going
deeper you feel more peaceful and the
first time a guy runs you off the road
it changes and then there's a deeper
meditation that has the power to change
this world into a different kind of
realm and there are other planets where
they already did it and are we're like
the retards at the back of the class
okay our planet on a galactic level is
considered we call it [__] but
there's a polite word with
developmentally disagree or they should
call our planet DD
okay the DD planet so this planet in
among people who know okay it's
considered a little
and they're waiting for us to catch up
okay and it is possible to have a
perfect planet and it is possible not to
live in this kind of guts and bones body
and it's possible to change the body and
and not go through all the suffering
that that people go through in this
world okay and you have a certain window
in your life to make it happen you have
1020 years to make it happen if you
don't you get too old to think straight
and then you're back in and again okay
so you have a window of opportunity to
change things and to change things you
have to learn about what she's teaching
okay
so she's gonna start off on 25 different
kinds of meditation that don't work okay
and she's brutal she's not this sweet
angel okay she's like brutal in in
assessing these different kinds of
meditation and you have to understand
that these were meditations that were
popular in Tibet 500 years ago okay and
we have no commentary to this text we
don't know who he was criticizing but it
seems to be that certain mistakes in
meditation are universal they get
repeated every generation okay
every generation makes the same mistakes
inside of meditation okay so we're going
to go through 25 mistaken meditations
ineffective meditations they're not
going to help you in a big way
they're not gonna save you you know and
you can do them for a while and then
when you start to get older you get
scared
and you say I need something that's
gonna really work okay I call these
meditations fire extinguishers that
never work okay like people sell you a
fire extinguisher they say put it they
make a law that you have to have one in
each building
and they know they don't work but you
don't know until you have a fire that
they don't work you you pull them off
the wall and you push the button and
nothing happens and you're like oh my
gosh these cynical people are selling
fire extinguishers that don't work and
I'm about to lose my house you see so
that's the experience that many people
have as they get older that you're
closer to death and they realized that
the meditation was ineffectual it wasn't
strong it wasn't effective it was it was
sweet it was nice the teacher was nice
it felt good and and now when push comes
to shove it it they realize they need
something more okay so the point of
studying this text is to identify those
kinds of meditation ahead of time so at
least you can think about it you know
somebody said you know one of the
greatest Buddhists who ever lived the
first pension Amma said these don't work
be careful you know if you're doing one
of them think about it and and try to do
something that does work and the 26th
the meditation is one that does work
okay and we won't get to it I don't know
I don't know we're gonna get to it okay
so Willie will hear 25 meditations
they're not stupid meditations they are
attractive they are sophisticated they
are interesting they feel good and they
don't help you with the big things okay
so you know the idea is get familiar
with them and my experience has been by
the way at Diamond Mountain we're gonna
cover eight of them because Lord Buddha
covered eight of them many you know two
and a half thousand years ago he said
here's eight meditations that don't work
and here's a ninth one that does work
and he called it the roar of the lion
the meditation is called the dance of
the lion
okay so he said use these go through
these date meditations that you will
hear about get used to them
suck suck some benefit out of them get
to another nine number nine and leave
the other eight okay so we're gonna
cover that at Diamond Mountain these
twenty five are included in I mean the
eight are included in these twenty five
okay you will see them here but if you
come to them Mountain when we leave
tomorrow starts on front Friday we'll do
it together okay I thought tonight I
don't have time to do twenty five
meditations with you I will describe
them but if you have time come to the
mountain will actually sit there we'll
take you through them you see how they
feel you test drive at least eight of
them okay for an hour or something and
then then you'll see what's you'll see
why they don't really work okay got it
so tonight I'm just describing them if
you want to go deeper if you want to
play with them and see their strengths
and their weaknesses then come to the
mountain and that's what we'll be doing
okay alright because we have you know I
don't know I'll be there for two weeks
or something all right here we go so
here's the what he called here's the
segue that whole so far has just been a
kind of cute argument between the devil
and the angel in one guy's mind
I assume it's our mind right your mind
and then the devil says oh once and well
somebody comes along they say they're a
great meditator they say they're gonna
throw me out of the mind and they say
I'm gonna meditate on the mind as it
really is okay and then we start the
first row meditation okay first of
twenty-five I've numbered them for you
okay I was curious because I was
wondering how many how many is he going
to go through
I call it flaccid meditation okay
he flaccid means you make a flagpole out
of rubber or you know it means it's not
gonna be as strong as you need okay it's
not gonna work okay it's just like huh
it's gonna when you need it when when
things get hard like death is on its way
this meditation is not gonna it's like
having a plastic knife in a in a gang
finer son you know like a rubber knife
in a gang fight or something
it's gonna be that useful when the when
when the poop hits the fan in the in the
dangerous parts of your life as you you
know you get in that final car accident
or something and you pull out this
meditation it's gonna be like a rubber
knife you know in a gang fight it's it's
it's just like bling-bling
okay that's what I mean I'm trying to
give you this picture the meditation is
it's not effective it's not gonna help
you it's sweet it's interesting it feels
good the teacher was nice you know they
used a lot of sanskrit words and it's
not gonna help you okay
in when you need it it's not gonna help
you okay
all right first one those of you who
know the DCI system I based the present
moment meditation on this one okay this
was an ancient meditation that said try
to stay in the present moment okay don't
let the mind and there's a there's a
practice you can do it takes about an
hour to explain it okay but you first
you watch your mind you see if you are
straying off to the future and straying
off to the past and I've been in groups
of a thousand or two thousand people we
sat down altogether we meditated John
has John and Connie have led these
meditations and we asked people to vote
we were in Moscow a couple weeks ago we
did it and we asked people to vote do
you have more future thoughts or more
past thoughts you know are you living in
the future are you
you know usually past is the ex husband
or wife future is usually you know
something you hope to happen next week
and most people are living in one or the
other okay and that sort of makes you
what do you call it unable to function
because you're never in the present you
see it's like being on your phone all
day it's like you're never here in this
real world you're in some virtual
reality you know there's people who
stare at that all day or they stare at
their laptop all day and they never
experienced the world you see the
outside of these electrons you know
they'll say look at this picture of a
tree you know I'll say but don't you
want to go touch a tree no no look
there's another tree you know and it's
like that so is it a useful practice yes
is it nice to be in the present moment
yes is it helpful to be in the present
moment yes a good meditator should be
able to identify whether they're in the
present moment or not they should get
that good at watching their mind am i
wandering towards my ex-wife or am i
wandering towards what's gonna happen
when I get home what's in my fridge
after geshe-la finishes tonight you see
I had a meditation teacher Goenka who
started the piscina and I spent ten days
with him in 1973 and he was the first
thing he said he got up and he said
don't think about monkeys during the
next ten days don't think about monkeys
then we meditated hard for ten days and
of course all we could think about was
monkeys try to be in the present moment
okay is that an ultimately healthful
meditation no the present moment will
get older and older you'll get older and
older and you will die in the present
moment okay it's useful it's it's a it's
a slightly useful tool but it's not the
goal okay it's like watching your breath
which is what Goenka teaches talk which
is what his students still teach watch
your breath it it doesn't help you
change your life it gives you focus it
makes you peaceful it puts you in the
present moment and then you die
okay life will push you out of the
present moment okay that's the nature of
life you need something more it's a good
it's a good start to be in the present
moment
it's a nice thing it's useful we teach
it DCI has a present moment meditation
but it's not the goal okay it's like
watching your breath it's not the goal
in your life to count the breath as the
end 17 was it there's a number they put
on it in the yoga tradition when it's 17
million eight hundred thousand something
how many breaths you will breathe in
your night okay then they end ok now
this is going to be it's funny because
the devil knows what's a good meditation
the the devil in this case is
sophisticated ok so don't ever think
Devils are stupid if you have time to
read there's a book by CS Lewis who did
the Narnia books is called the Screwtape
Letters and it's advice to his nephew
from the devil on how to corrupt a young
man in England during World War two ok
and it's and they I read an interview
with CS Lewis and he said it was the
hardest book he ever wrote because he
had to put his mind in the devil's mind
you know to talk to write what the devil
was saying he had to think like the
devil and it was painful to think like
the devil but the the thing he pointed
out was Devils are not stupid they are
extremely intelligent
you know this devil in the Screwtape
Letters he says what's the greatest
thing that happened to Devils in the
last hundred years and you know his
nephews like I don't know you we
corrupted like 10 million people he says
no no we got people not to believe in
the devil
that's an achievements
you know when you talk about the demo
people think you're foolish or you're
not sophisticated this is the best thing
we ever did
no one even believes me exists and we're
in everybody's mind you know it's so
cool okay all right this devil is
similar so what he will say continually
these people who are doing a lesser
meditation are actually meditating on me
okay and that's a very serious charge
are you saying Geshe Michael that to do
breath meditation is to meditate on the
devil come on you know calm down
it's maybe a waste of time but it's not
evil the devil is evil you know watching
your breath for five years you know
other kinds of meditation like that
they're not evil they're just a waste of
time you know but the devil here says no
you are meditating on me okay why
somebody tell me why bigger than that
connected to my drive today yeah say it
again yeah even as you're watching your
breath you are misunderstanding the
entire world okay how you feel about
your breath where does your breath come
from
oh my mom gave me my breath and I ate
Cheerios this morning so I have life and
then I have breath and that's why I have
life you know and and Buddhism says no
the reason you enjoy any moment of
living is because you protected life in
the past okay and that's the only reason
you get to live five minutes more okay
so while you're watching your breath you
don't understand your breath and you're
making your negativities stronger okay
every moment you think the breath is
coming from your mom or from the
food you ate today or the yoga you did
this afternoon then you are you are
strengthening the devil inside of you
okay every moment you look at anything
and don't understand it the devil is
getting stronger inside of you and he
will kill you okay literally he will
kill you okay what am I supposed to
thinking huh
at least think I'm breathing because I
protected life I respected life I did
not kill people animals trees okay I
respected life and that's why I have the
gift of breath that's why I have five
minutes more to breathe
you see that's in God's angel thinking
right be careful
somebody contradict me because we're
going to go there sooner or later
is it the angel to focus on your breath
during of a positive meditation and at
least think I'm breathing because I
protected life I respected life it's
that the angel know and we're gonna get
there we're gonna get there okay is that
the perception of emptiness no what's
the how would you express the perception
the emptiness at that moment oh I would
kiss you but your husband's here yeah
there's no I breath which you are
breathing which didn't come from
protecting life is impossible that's the
only idea that can give you progress
okay guess not it's the same thing is
understanding your breaths coming from
protecting life no it's not the same
thing
okay one is positive one is negative
okay oh I'll show you why are you
breathing Geshe Michael because my mom
and my dad you know they were messing
around in 1951
now that's just straight devil okay now
here's a more subtle demo okay so I why
are you breathing I protected life in
the past okay in this subtle subtle
subtle book it's not enough to stop
there okay you have to go to what's not
there you have to express it as what's
not there you have okay you're ready
here I go here's the best one I'm not
breathing because my mother gave me life
I'm not breathing cuz I respected life
okay sorry I am no I take that back
yeah I'm not breathing because I take
vitamin supplements okay that's that's a
higher meditation the negative side is a
higher meditation okay
and we're get there we'll get there it's
around 21 or something okay and it's
subtle it's subtle the first one in
Buddhism what's that stupid inconvenient
name for it this breath comes from
protecting life yeah it's dependent
origination things come from causes
that's true but it's not ultimate truth
okay what's ultimate truth all the
things you think everything you see
everything you encounter in your life
you are wrong it's not just a guy who
ran you off the road
it's your foot it's the chair it's
Sedona okay you you're wrong about
everything all the time okay got it
who made who made the building John
Brady Canio O'Brien Oh Brady they made
the building no they didn't who gave the
steel the strength of the steel who put
the strength in this deal I gave this
lecture at the World Trade Center in
1999 I said who put the strength in this
steel I did and then I got out of New
York I went on a three-year retreat I
was the last person in America to hear
about it
they interviewed me the newspaper name
you know who put the strength in this
deal okay you did okay you someone
needed housing in Puerto Rico or Mexico
City and you donated you donated money
okay to Mexico City all right and that's
why the that put the strength in the
steel and if you don't donate money to
Mexico City you'll be in the World Trade
Center when it falls down okay that's
real meditation okay here we go
mmm okay so that's number one is it a
good thing to be in the present moment
yes is it useful to meditate on that
occasionally yes does it sharpen your
meditative ability yes is it the goal no
it doesn't help you it doesn't save you
you can be in the present moment until
you die and then that's it it's end of
meditation okay mmm use the meditation
for something that will change the world
don't use it for feeling good for half
an hour until you get in a traffic jam
okay now here's ineffective meditation
number two don't forget we got twenty
five to go oh we're not doing too bad
okay the trap of emptying the mind
that's what I call it okay here's how
she describes it other people try to
stop the mind from thinking about
anything their meditation consists of
being careful not to think at all but
here's the test whether a meditation is
good or not okay
does anybody remember what's the test
it's called incompatibility now you
explain it
that's that's true he said but you know
and logically you have to be careful to
say one object and then you have to say
entirely cold or entirely hot at the
same time burn your hand and freeze your
hand at the same time no one object
frying pan that you put on the stove for
for an hour and tell us red hot okay and
then you put it in the freezer for two
days then you touch it okay it can't be
red hot and frozen at the same time
either or okay the whole pan I'm not
talking yeah theoretically you could
heat up the handle and not heat up the
end of it or something like that but
that's called contradiction what's
contradiction here what's the
contradiction this whole book is about
yeah the devil cannot occupy hi John
Foley the devil cannot occupy the same
space as the angel okay they don't get
along and they never will okay they
cannot live in the same mind they cannot
stay in the same head this town ain't
big enough for both of us somebody has
to leave okay that's the idea why are
they incompatible she's beautiful and
kind he's got horns and me is that why
they're incompatible come on come on
what do we see last night yeah the way
they see things is is cannot be
reconciled there will never be a
marriage between these two why one of
them believes that life comes from
saving life okay the other believes it
comes from chemicals and vitamins and
your mom and your doctor and okay garden
is it wrong to take vitamins do their
work if you protect life your vitamin
supplements will work if you don't
protect life if you eat life and then
take the vitamin supplements they might
hurt you
daddy you can't have it both ways either
the world is coming from how you tree
other people or the world is just random
okay you can do whatever you want as
long as you nobody's watching okay do
what you want
okay those the way the devil looks at
the world and the way that angel looked
at the world are completely incompatible
she thinks the guy who ran me off the
road tonight was coming from me because
I push people too hard
okay and he thinks the guy got in his
car he had a beer you know me and my
friend said at the Beaver Creek mini
market one night me and Anatole I said
let's have fun he said what I said let's
count how many beers leave this store
this convenience store in the next 45
minutes guess what the number was 490
and I live in that town I don't drive
after fire no I mean see the devil will
blame it on the beer you see the devil
will blame the guy's diming on the beer
okay the angel will say why he drank a
beer because you made him drink a beer
and don't blame him okay you did
something dangerous in the past so you
have to see something then yes okay
they're incompatible the way she views
the world and the way he views the world
are completely incompatible
all right so in in ineffective
meditation number two it's called empty
of mind
don't think about anything okay which is
a joke because the harder you think
about it you're thinking about not
thinking about anything you can't not
you can't think about nothing but the
harder you try the more obvious it
becomes that you can't okay now why is
that an ineffective meditation why is it
flabby
why is it it's not useless this just
doesn't have any strength all right
right
it's got no avocado
wait do you know what that joke means we
need a Mexican to explain into it I was
in Guadalajara this lady explained to me
it was Susana it's not me okay
she said avocado is Azteca for God's
testicles I said I didn't know but I
don't like him anyway
anyway this second meditation has no
avocado you understand okay why now now
you have the ammunition now you can tell
me why tell me why why is it weak why is
it not very helpful yeah thinking about
nothing is not the opposite of how the
devil looks at stuff you see we want a
meditation that contradicts the devil we
don't want a meditation that can coexist
with the devil got it it's okay empty
your mind and it's not gonna hurt your
opinion that the guy ran you off the
road because he had a beer okay I'll say
it again emptying your mind for an hour
or two hours in the morning it's not
gonna make you understand the guy who
ran you off the road okay it's not going
to contradict the feeling that he was
drunk and it's his fault okay we're
looking for a meditation which will
drive the devil out of the mind we're
looking for a meditation that the devil
cannot coexist with and there's only one
and that's the meditation that says my
breath is coming from respecting life
okay and everything else is flossing
flabby that the devil's gonna say yeah
come on Yin you can stay for a half hour
you want to meditate on your breath yeah
come on sit here next to me meditate on
your breath it doesn't hurt me okay
hey this whole poem you know hundreds of
page
The Devil's like oh you want to man you
better come sit next to me in the mind
together how long you want to do that 45
minutes I'm a real meditator oh yeah
sure sit down next to me you don't hurt
me you you're just like nothing you know
I sit next to an avocado I sit next to
you is the same okay doesn't hurt me you
can't stand this mind rest of your life
you can meditate on your breath rest
your life it doesn't do anything to me
it doesn't endanger me at all
Gani we're looking for a meditation okay
I commuted for 19 years to Manhattan two
hours each way to earn money for the
monastery okay and I don't know Port
Authority used to go she knows to drive
so you're the last one on the bus bus
holds 49 people you're the last one on
the bus you got the only empty seat next
year you're like I dunno the point is
what we're looking for our fat guy who
who can't sit on the same bench with
with the devil you see we want a
meditation that's so fast that the devil
has to move okay got it when the when
that meditation comes into the mind the
devil has to leave for half hour okay
that's what we're looking for we don't
want a meditation that allows for
coexistence okay well any meditation
which allows the devil to remain while
you're doing it is a mistake okay it's
not good enough it doesn't hurt the down
he said yes
oh you want to you want to pretend
there's no thoughts in your mind come on
come on your mind power
long as this mind is thinking about that
I'm safe got it because you don't
contradict the way I look at things okay
you don't contradict the way I look at
things you're not gonna take over this
mind you're not gonna push me out of
this mind okay yeah go ahead
empty your mind empty your thoughts do
not all be I love it we can live
together okay we go common-law marriage
all right any effective meditation
number doing now in effect of emptiness
this is called gentle this was a wrong
idea about emptiness that was popular in
Tibet 500 years ago okay
emptiness means cancel something
emptiness means cancel something okay
that's the that's the meaning of
emptiness okay now I'll I'll ask you
guys who are you know experienced about
these subjects ready are you canceling
something that exists or are you
canceling something that never could
exist never could okay a guy okay
no breath that could come from your
vitamin supplements okay it could not
exist there's no such thing okay it
never existed okay what catch that you
take vitamin supplements yeah I do but I
protect life at the same time so they
were going okay I loaded my supplements
for dime man it's like an hour because
every doctor I have gives me more and
none of them ever says okay you can stop
some of them own the supplement company
okay that's okay as long as I protect
life and they give me I don't know
rabbit pellets it'll work okay okay so
here's the third one
this is more subtle okay is the mind of
physical thing in Buddhism
No okay it's based on a physical thing
it's it's it's based on your physical
body it's it's not the brain but it you
can say it's based on the brain if you
inject the brain with certain chemicals
if you inject the brain with wine the
mind gets stupid okay if you if you
submit the mind to stress the physical
body will get an ulcer or a heart attack
okay they're connected but they're
separate okay so the mind lives in the
body but the mind is not physical okay
it's it's invisible okay there's a link
but it's not a same thing okay so can we
say you ready can we say that the mind
has an absence of material stuff yeah
okay it's like your foot has an absence
of your hand okay are they exist yeah
they exist but but is the foot the
absence of your hand yeah partly okay if
the foot wasn't the absence of your hand
you'd have a hand growing off your foot
okay guys so you could say that chair is
not the brain it's not the mind okay
he's the chair does the chair have
emptiness of mind yeah yeah it does
there's no mind in the chair okay is
that is that ultimate emptiness that
will help you no okay
why well the thing that's not in the
chair really exists you see you've got
to have irony here you got to have an
iron here you'd have to have tragedy
here the thing that messes up the world
doesn't exist and never existed I was in
Kiev you know we had a great program two
weeks ago you know there was a record
attendance 306 people for two-day
program and we we slowly got to the
point that your enemy doesn't exist you
see what I mean it's like the guy who
ran me off the road
right he doesn't exist the one that I'm
the one that's not my fault
never existed okay got it
so emptiness that helps you is to
realize that what you thought was
hurting you wasn't even there
120 million people died in World War two
120 million people dying in World War
two the enemy didn't exist I was in care
I'm talking to Ukrainian they suffered
during World War two
you know huge casualties tens of
millions of people then I'm like and we
got to this beautiful moment like you
understand
there was no hitting me in World War two
and they're like yeah we got it
they're like wow okay guarding just not
okay so emptiness doesn't work unless
it's the absence of something that was
never there emptiness doesn't help you
until you understand the thing that's
not there it's something that can't
exist anyway it's not the emptiness of
money or the emptiness of love or the
Antonis of you see it's the emptiness of
a ghost or a phantom or something that
was never there every enemy in your life
wasn't there every person who ever
irritated you in your life was never
there they were your reflection okay and
we are extremely forgiving of us if me
drives me off the road oh that's okay
you know you can make a mistake once in
a while okay but it was always you
so show other people the same okay okay
so number three don't go there was an
idea in too bad of a wrong school that
said gentle gentle means the mind is
empty of everything else okay so how
does it help you okay the mind is empty
of dog food but that
help you okay it's true there's no dog
food in your mind but it doesn't help
you okay it was the wrong idea it's now
who's that I won't say there's still
some people trying it okay now there's a
thing called sim Jimbo say stem Jimbo
Sam Jimbo it's called
in Jimbo in Tibetan has two meanings one
is naked and one is raw the raw
vegetables are called say jumbo naked
person is called me Jimbo okay and there
was a school in Tibet that said the goal
of meditation is to see the naked mind
get down to the core of the mind and
then you are meditating okay
meet the mind face-to-face okay without
elaborations without distracting
thoughts without other kinds of mental
activity meet the source of the mind and
that's meditation okay now what's our
test about whether it's a useful
meditation or effective meditation or
not
what's our test does it make the devil
uncomfortable
is he like if this meditation gets on
the bus does the devil have to change to
another chair
you see that's the test of a good
meditation okay if you meet the mind
face the face will it stop you the next
time someone runs you off the road from
getting angry will it make you realize
he was your fault
no to watch the naked mind to meet the
naked mind will it make you understand
where the guy came from no so we say we
wasted time is it sweet yes
is it cool yes it's nice to look at the
Grand Canyon no it is but it's not gonna
it's not gonna kill your death it's not
gonna stop your death it's nice it's
okay no problem but don't don't think
it's gonna help you in the poop hits the
fan
okay that's wrong meditation number four
it's called Nick and mine we're going
pretty well right we'll stop in like 15
minutes
take a refreshment break and then we'll
do question and answer okay for half an
hour so if you we we like hard questions
that's art tsongkhapa lineage we
specialize in hard questions so you have
half an hour to think of some hard
questions they don't have to be about
this subject there can be any kind of
hard question you can also ask an easy
question Berger okay now there's another
one called song tell some tell was a
meditation that people did and they it's
called we would call it rambling
meditation mind running you know not
your mind ramble okay
just ramble watch your mind the bar ride
the cars ride the tiger of the mind okay
they all have sexy names okay and
they're all useless there's like those
anyway I won't mention in the in the in
the vitamin supplements area they have
beautiful names and they don't do
anything okay
so this one was called rambling mine
song tell it's an ancient word it just
means to let your mind ramble and don't
try to meditate and that's a kind of
meditation okay like let the mind blah
blah and just watch it and don't don't
fight just relax be here now let the
mind ramble don't don't try to resist
this rambling mind okay let him ramble
that's that's so stupid
there's some of them I don't have to
explain right okay but by the way he
says here's here's what the devil said
this has nothing to do with meditating
watching the mind ramble has nothing to
do with meditating on you wisdom and in
I can report that I have never seen you
in those people's minds during that
meditation okay the devil's reporting to
the angel you know I've known a lot of
Rambler meditators and I was thinking
did I ever meet you doing those no I
never saw you in there okay
the devil says the angel I never you
never showed your face during one of
those okay that's a way of saying it was
a waste of time okay number six
uneducated meditation okay meditate with
no training okay if you want take a 200
hour yoga training they'll talk about
meditation for two-three hours and then
they'll set them loose on the world and
I was in I took a class in Phoenix a
couple weeks ago and I sat down and I
said I hope they don't meditate me for
in yoga cuz it gets me riled up and then
the lady said that's many thing I know
and then she said we're gonna watch the
breath for ten breaths if you think of
something else stop and go back to one
which came from me and I'm like which I
mean it's an old Tibetan technique but I
translated the text and made it popular
so I'm like she doesn't know that the
guy who translated is in the room and I
said but it's cool it makes me feel like
a grandfather or something you know I'm
like that's so cool and then she did
that and when she got to the end she
said now think about nothing I wanted to
throw them yoga block on her but it's
okay so that's called uneducated
meditation okay and most of them are
meditating on me okay why you see even
as they observe their mind in their
heart they don't understand that the
mind is flowing from how they treated
people last week
okay people I can't concentrate care huh
why what's happening I get this blah
blah in my mind I can't stop it
you will never be able to stop it why
because you are blah blah two people
last week and you planted the kind of
seeds for blah blah so when you sit down
and close your eyes you hear blah blah
okay you put the blah blah in your mind
alright because last week you were blah
blah and wasting other people's mind
other people's time you were telling
them the 289,000 story about Trump that
they didn't hear you okay give it up let
it go blah blah there's somebody about
Trump give it up
seven more years or whatever we can do
it stop talking don't blah blah
why not it puts seeds in your mind for
blah blah
then when you try to meditate you can't
maintain why cuz you put karmic seeds in
your mind for blah blah got in okay so
the every time you meditate and watch
your mind and you don't think about what
I hear in my mind is coming from what I
said last week you are strengthening the
devil okay every hour you meditate and
watch the mind without once thinking
what I observe is coming from how I
treated people last week then you are
strengthening the devil in your mind and
you will be less able to understand next
week what you hear in your mind okay
because you're you're perpetuating a bad
habit okay
lazy meditation is not just an icy
meditation it hurts you next week it's a
bad habit okay and then it gets stronger
so just to meditate on the mind is to
strengthen the negative market you see
okay just being unaware of what's really
happening in your mind is to strengthen
your unawareness for next time okay
what you hear in your mind as you
meditate
is directly coming from seeds that were
planted when you heard yourself talk
last week to somebody blah blah blah and
then in my my my my my you can't believe
ok doesn't mean you shouldn't be
well-informed no it doesn't mean that I
to the economists it's correct you know
it's it's a good solid news you learn
things you should be up on current
events you should know what a central
bank is and why they're messing things
up
like you should understand okay but just
blah blah about some politician who's an
idiot come on
even though anyway I'm not gonna do it
okay
ineffective meditation number seven is
called child hiding under a blanket so I
don't know if you know but if of course
I I think probably your kids did this
they think when when you catch them
doing something bad little kids they
will cover their head with a blanket and
somehow because they can't see you they
think you can't see them some ball
probably does this okay got that they
the kid will put a blanket over their
head because they don't want you to see
them but what you see is a kid with a
blanket or with him that they can't see
you so they think everything's okay okay
okay this is this kind of meditation so
this is tricky does the devil exists or
not
that's just asking you a question yes or
no
yeah is there a state of mind in your
mind and doesn't understand the guy who
ran you off the road tonight yeah I have
a devil in my kitchen Michael proved
this evening when he got irritated I was
even thinking which finger to show the
guy but I couldn't catch up to him okay
so I do have the devil in mine okay I do
have the devil in my mind is there
sometimes an absence of the devil in my
mind yeah I mean tonight
I calm down I I'm supposed to be the
teacher I have to talk about how the guy
who was driving unsafely came from me
okay
so during that moment of truth humility
rare moment the devil had to move out
for two minutes the devil had to wait
over here
then when I stopped talking he came back
so was there an absence of the devil in
my mind while I was talking about where
the guy really came from yeah was there
an absence of the devil in my mind when
I was upset at the guy driving badly be
careful go deeper what's the devil in my
mind or not
what's the devil as I see the devil in
my mind or not
yeah but what's that mean don't give me
plot Buddhist platitudes good good okay
so even as you recognize the devil in
your mind you you don't you're
strengthening him because you don't
reflect that he came from the devil last
week okay I last week I got pissed at a
driver another driver also and that
event
strengthened the devil so he could come
back this week who's responsible for the
devil in my mind who put him in my mind
not the guy in the road who put the
devil in this road I mean okay got it so
it's not enough to meditate on the
absence of the devil because there's a
relative absence and there's a real
absence okay what's the relative absence
well I'm thinking about the angel the
devil can't be there okay that's easy
but even while the devil's not there I'm
thinking about the devil in the wrong
way and there's no devil like ton
there's an absence of Doug devil the
options of the devil that didn't come
because I misunderstood the devil last
week it's more important okay understand
why is the devil in my mind this way
what's the seats for the devil what's
the karmic seeds for the devil it's
simply not understanding him okay every
day you spend not understanding devil is
planning more seeds to have them in your
mind okay so is there an absence of a
devil in your mind all the time
yeah that's the real angel okay I'm not
supposed to know okay so it's not enough
to to say the devil's not in my mind
it's not enough to say the devil is
empty okay you have to understand what
it means it means there's no devil in my
mind who didn't come from me okay but
this guy hasn't been meditating on he's
trying to pretend he doesn't have the
because some Buddhist Lama said nothing
exists okay so yeah okay so I don't have
ignorant in my mind I thought I did okay
all right this was called flaccid
philosophy I got to give him better
names if someone wants to help me give
him better names I'm up for it I was in
a rush okay this is number eight
flaccid philosophy means blah blah
philosophy okay blah blah blah blah
about emptiness blah blah blah blah and
then the person still gets angry at the
first person that made who irritates
them that means they're just talking
about philosophy and they're not living
philosophy okay so this this meditation
number eight useless meditation number
eight is is logic not aimed at yourself
okay logic not aimed at improving Geshe
Michael okay and that's next kind of
useless meditation it's their emptiness
yes how many divisions two what person
and things does the second school expect
it agree that the emptiness and things
exist no they only accept the emptiness
in their person oh really yeah but some
of the third school except the fourth
quarter so they're doing something for
school you know and then the person
doesn't improve themselves they just
talked about all these ideas okay so
this meditation is is thinking about the
ideas but missing the main point which
is apply it to you okay the reason the
Buddha taught all these different
schools is that on different days we
need different schools okay and we have
to apply them to ourself or else it's
just another flabby meditation okay
rubber knife at a street fight okay
although I did see Jason Bourne killed
somebody with a pen
okay we had a good place to take a break
look we've done eight useless
meditations I think the big ones are
empty your mind try to think about
nothing or just let thoughts run to your
mind watch them come and go like clouds
in the sky bla bla bla it doesn't help
you it doesn't improve you it makes you
a passive watcher of the crap going to
your mind it's not going to help you
okay some small help not not serious
okay
it doesn't hurt the devil okay so here
[Music]
some people are meditating on nothing
more than me
and sometimes they're meditating are
nothing more than nothing and sometimes
there are many thing I'm trying to think
of nothing a person is meditating on
these things
bla bla is hurting me okay a person
who's meditating on where the other
driver really came from is hurting me
then he calls it and then we'll take a
break
Nick you ready me me me me me karma me
me come on boy come on good but what's
karma me good a star that shines in the
sky at noon that's how common is a
meditator who's really meditating on
something that hurts me okay they're
about as common as the North Star coming
out in the blue sky okay
who said that the devil he's not stupid
he's not stupid he's sophisticated okay
all right
he says a person who really understands
this stuff
it's about as common as a star shining
in the middle of the day then he says
something very powerful and then we'll
stop I don't know why but it happens to
be verse number 108
if you're not gonna change that
situation stop hassling me who's talking
talking to the angel and then he says
you miss angel are an odd number of dumb
butter flour Oh dumb butter flower this
flower is a cobalt Lotus it opens once
every thousand years so he accuses her
of being what's an Englishman I don't
know or it has to be an example of
something that only happens every
thousand years like I don't know Joe's
comment going to the sky or something
you know you just visit this mind every
thousand years I live here who's talking
yeah okay in the very best of
circumstances you might come but only
once and even that requires that the
person spend an inconceivable number of
millions of years doing good things to
other people to get you to come in their
mind for 10 minutes requires millions of
good Karma's they have to help thousands
of other people to get you into the mind
for 10 minutes so I'm set you know and
then he says something cool okay what
and that can only come by pleasing the
one who is your mama okay
shortcut to the angel shortcut to the
angel you know find your personal
teacher it doesn't have to be gushing
Michael you find your personal teacher
maybe it's your mom maybe it's your wife
maybe it's your kid okay but every
person on a spiritual path has to have
somebody watching them helping them okay
and you and the first thing in life is
to find one and it might be anywhere
okay by the way where are they coming
from I always tell people you don't have
to go to India and get diary
okay cuz that's all that most people get
when they're gonna in their plan to
cease to meet this person draw this
person to your community like a bee to
honey
okay what's the honey be kind to the
people around you and you will attract
your heart Lama like a bee they can't
avoid it
okay how do you get a heart Lama do you
have to buy an Air India ticket trust me
you don't want to any other ticket but
not Air India okay
and see you don't get them by going to
find them you get them the way you get
anything else you plant the seed and
then they have to come they don't have a
choice okay
got it and you can sit in your house and
plant the seed and they'll knock on your
door okay
there's anyway there's many stories like
that okay but but if you want the Karma
to have the angel in your mind you can
you can do thousands of good things to
other people or you can find your heart
teacher and have a good honest healthy
relationship with them and and that's
enough karma to have the angel move into
your mind okay
shortcut easy okay don't don't spend the
rest your life without a personal
teacher find them which means you have
to plant them and it doesn't have to be
me it could be anybody it's up to you a
lot of people find out that the person
they've been living with for 20 years is
their heart lower but they didn't know
okay got it we you don't know who it is
okay but once you find them the Karma of
that relationship is enough to for the
angel to move in okay cool it's the
easiest Karma it's the most powerful
Karma okay we'll take a break 15 minutes
okay Tim there's refreshments across the
way here you're welcome to go have some
and come back with some good questions
okay
okay questions anybody have a question
miss Paula no Nick chooses then no one
gets mad at me don't ask me you can't
ask me a hard question
wait her mics not on okay you said early
on that this dependent origination logic
was not far enough so why is it that je
tsongkhapa wrote in praise of dependent
origination as being the way to find
emptiness yeah good good question so if
we take it out of Buddhist terminology
dependent origination names I see a guy
driving recklessly because I was
reckless last week so and by the way the
way karma is planted in your mind is by
your own awareness of yourself so you
know if I was speaking recklessly last
the week before and I hear myself
talking that's what plants karma in my
mind so I say something reckless it goes
through my eardrum and it brushes my
mind it makes an impression called a Sun
SCARA and then two hours later that's
called a vasana and it stays in my
subconscious mind so that's dependent
origination in Buddhist terms planting a
seed for the guy to run me off the road
planning it last week is its dependent
origination it's the positive side of
reality things seeds are planted and
things are coming from seeds the
opposite of that is nothing's any other
way
nothing is any other way okay and that's
emptiness okay so like a guy that could
run me off the road
who wasn't coming from what I did last
week is impossible it's an impossibility
the goal of Buddhist meditation is to
meet that emptiness face to face
and that's that experience does
something to your soul it makes a
permanent change in your being and and
you cannot help but become an angel
within a certain amount of time if you
meet it directly the absence of the guy
you thought was there okay in meditation
it permanently changes your your being
and and within a short period of time
you become what what would be called an
angel in the West you become so to see
that things are coming from your seats
doesn't help the other thing to see that
nothing's not coming from your seats
that's the other thing so in your
meditation you have to push you we're
gonna push up to like down Mountain
we'll start tomorrow next day day after
tomorrow push up to observing the seeds
opening and then go find her and that's
what changes your being that has some
indelible effect on your being and it
forces you to change into a divine being
within a certain amount of time you
don't have a choice after that you can't
stop the process okay so so to stop at
the seeds watching the seeds open is is
a subtle form of the devil
when did some cover appraises yeah he
just means it's the best place to step
off from to get to emptiness that's all
yeah I mean he he wrote thousands of
pages about emptiness he wrote one poem
about dependent today so don't hassle me
what transcending a book in which which
is 1200 pages along you know we're we're
about halfway through okay next question
I guess oh this is from the live stream
live stream room from Bonnie's bonnie
down in phoenix
well tell her thanks she wants to know
wouldn't the naked mind you were
speaking of earlier beat emptiness and
if not what is the gotcha that one would
reach who saw the naked mind be
mistakenly focused on it yeah okay good
so Sam Jimba naked mind as it was used
historically by these people invented
this meditation you would say is
something like watching the deep
processes of your mind without being
aware of seats okay so it would be
stripping away the it'd be watching the
the subtle levels of consciousness in
your mind so there's a principle in
meditation which is called shiitake
number Chen Shiraki number 10 means and
we're gonna learn it at Diamond Mountain
this weekend but it's the process of
upgrading you see economy class doesn't
look bad until you've flown business
class for a while I have a sponsor he's
flown me around business class last year
and now economy class looks like torture
you know but then recently when I went
to get my business class seat there was
somebody in it and I said you know hi
guy
you know I'm a Buddhist I'm not gonna
hassle you but you can sit on my lap but
I'm not sitting on your lap you know and
any I said this is my seat I showed him
my ticket then we both had the same
ticket and then he went to the with me
now he called the referee which is the
stewardess and she said you're mr. Ross
I said yeah Oh we'll be up good to get a
first class yeah you're supposed to be
in the front of the plane you know and
I'm like oh you take this team but this
is called a shiitake number 10 it means
peaceful by comparison peaceful by
comparison so we do it in the nine steps
of the lion stance right in that
meditation you start by focusing on the
sound of the air conditioner okay if you
don't have an air conditioner you can
have a kid okay
it means you gotta have some disturbing
noise in your house okay that doesn't
have anything that's called design room
okay then you upgrade it within five
minutes you consciously upgrade to the
sound of your heartbeat okay because
it's it's business class compared to
economy the economy is the sound of your
air conditioner and business class is
the sound of your heartbeat okay and
then you upgrade you stay there for a
few minutes then you upgrade to being
the heartbeat then you upgrade to being
in a crystal of sugar a single crystal
of sugar within your heart you put your
mind inside in there then you upgrade
quieter to spreading your mind out as
wide as the universal okay then you
upgrade to blocking out you block out
you go black you go unconscious you know
no processes then you upgrade to not
caring whether you're having an thought
process or not okay all of those are
called shiitake number ten they do
nothing to hurt the devil they're cute
they're cool they're interesting they're
fascinating you can spend hours on it
and they do nothing to hurt your opinion
that the guy ran you off the road
because of a beer they do nothing to
make you understand that he's coming
from you okay so they're considered a
ladder to get to the right place
and and it's upgrading to deeper quiet
okay so there's eight ways to upgrade to
a deeper sense of silence but when you
get to the last one you have to go the
ultimate silence what's there yeah
there's no guy who could hurt me who's
not coming from what I did last week
okay got it so so you it's okay to learn
to move up through quieter places and
more silent places but in the end you
have to switch over to a higher silence
okay why am I talking about that what
was the question
oh yeah so naked mind Bonnie
means just before he started thinking
about emptiness okay it's it's the
quietest place of your mind but it
doesn't help you it doesn't stop the
devil it doesn't work against the devil
it's just a quiet place in your mind so
in in that school in in the in the fifth
16th century in Tibet it was a school
that said if you got down to the place
where you blink everything out then that
was enlightenment or that's called the
naked mind so the quietest normal state
of mind that you can get to but it
doesn't help you it doesn't stop the
fire okay it doesn't put the fire out
it's it's nice and it's attractive and
it's peaceful but you can't stay there
okay other seats will open okay other
question Nick is choosing oh no he
always that's hardcore
so say where you're applying it this
technique to liked online meditation mhm
and so like some teachers will teach how
you know just the you imagine this you
imagine you're pulling
the cancer from another friend sorry so
so say when you're doing tonglen
meditation and you're doing the taking
right
it wouldn't be correct to teach that
meditation without defining with wisdom
what you're taking yeah that's a good
question that's a really good question
okay now we're gonna go at it this way
[Music]
mmm not understanding where the guy who
ran me off the road really comes from is
the seed for selfishness okay not
understanding where things come from
it's the seed for self-preservation
watching out for myself taking care of
me first
you see those all depend on
misunderstanding the world okay you
cannot be selfish if you understand the
way the world world really works okay
like you cannot compete you cannot ever
have the sense of competition if you
understand the way the world works
because the only way you can get
anything is to give it so the idea of
competition is fundamentally mistaken it
depends on the devil it depends on
thinking things just happen you see if
I'm faster stronger more intelligent I
will get more that that can only happen
that thought can only come in a mind
that doesn't understand that you plant
your future by how you treat other
people today you see what I mean
so the idea of competition is is
impossible in the mind of a person who
understands reality because they would
never try to be first
you see they would always offer first
place in the other person you see I mean
because that then they would be first
you see I mean so in the Tomlin
meditation where we agree to take
another person's pain into ourselves you
see I mean the resistance to it the
desire
the mind that thinks what the hell am i
doing why am I taking this person's
cancer I don't have cancer they have
cancer you know so in that meditation
you take it into yourself and and you're
working with this sense of selfishness
you see you don't want to have cancer
you'd rather somebody else had the
cancer you see I mean so we struggle
against your own mind your mind is like
yeah okay that's nice but let's not
really do it you know it's nice not to
have cancer I'm sorry they have cancer
and I you know but I'm not so noble I
would take it away from them and if on
myself if I could but that's coming from
a misunderstanding of why you're healthy
you're healthy because you did take
other people's pain in the past you see
what I mean
you're healthy because you did protect
life so you should be dying they're not
dying okay you should be very happy to
take other people's trouble I mean so
the what I mean is the sense of
selfishness and the misunderstanding of
the world are linked they're not the
same thing but selfishness comes
directly from misunderstanding the world
and I'll say it again like if I want to
have a successful company then I should
work really hard to have helped another
person make a successful company and
then I can't stop the success the
success will come so if you don't
understand that you wouldn't give your
time to another person starting a
business you would spend all your time
on your business you see what I mean so
selfishness is not the devil but it's
his eldest son
okay got it
so they're real aning they're related
but they're not the same yeah
so your question is if I'm just a plain
old dude and I'm trying to suck
somebody's cancer out of them by the way
in tone and meditation you destroy it
before it takes root in you obviously
okay
but you know in geshe-la am I supposed
to think that I'm seeing this cancer
because I didn't take because before you
said I mean am i required during a
meditation on kindness to think that the
problem the other person has the reason
I'm seeing it is because I helped him
make it am i required to think like done
yes okay yes all right when when you see
a person who has cancer it's partly
coming from you and and yeah you think
that while you're taking it away from
them and and and in Buddhism
that's called Ming Mitsuru attention
racing it's a very famous mantra it's
called love which sees nothing it's a
very famous it's the highest kind of
love it means you know you lost someone
you love a homeless person that you meet
a lot you meet a homeless person and you
feel good about yourself if you can love
them right like they irritate me in
Phoenix right the guy stands at the
intersection and it just irritates me
because I don't know what to do you know
I'm like you've got two legs you got two
arms I made this money you know I worked
for this money but but the Buddhists
love is supposed to think
I created this person so yeah yeah you
you are supposed to think even as you
give money to a poor person that you
created them okay yeah and then that's a
higher kind of love
and that kind of love never refuses to
give alright one more one more
mr. Nick so this question this question
is coming from Ayrton and Mexico Oh
Ayrton you're too hard
hey and where's your how come you're not
on the meditation chill up a meditation
group I haven't seen anything on what's
a cult what's up away from hassling him
way from the respond yeah so I didn't
see him I what's up the last few weeks
so the question you have a meditation
packed with the Guadalajara group yes so
the question he has is can you give us
an example of a coffee meditation Tartu
ocation that would be involve one of the
24 in an effective meditation 25 I think
that's good yeah that's really good so
coffee meditation means let's say I did
something good today
I don't know give me something good
today no well that's just something
normal anything what you do something
good today remember anything yeah okay
so coffee men so by giving someone a
rose you plant a karmic seed why because
you saw yourself let go of the rose and
that when you open your hand
that image entered your eye you touched
your cornea or whatever it is what's the
cells in the back optic cells optic
nerve and then that put an impression on
your mind and that planted a karma okay
so giving a rose plants a karma when you
are aware of what you did so karma can
only be planted by being aware of what
you do and that's what plants karma so
then you you plant the Karma
and then that karma can take a thousand
years to open you see karma sees never
never fade away cannot fade away they
must open but they they are like they
can sit in the mind for a thousand years
without opening and then suddenly open
okay they're just waiting for the right
conditions to open so it's possible that
things you do today the seed won't open
for a thousand years it's very normal
for that so there's a thing that Buddha
taught called tarte oak which is how you
get the seat to open faster and and if
you're really good at it you can make a
seat open the afternoon that you planted
in the morning okay if you if you know
that the method and you practice a lot
you can I have given away thirty
thousand dollars in the morning got in
fifty thousand dollars in cash you know
it happened I did it
so it's possible but you need to have
this we call the Saban do called the
Tartar took means you have to put water
on the scene okay how do you put water
on the scene you think I'm happy than I
did it okay you're like I'm I'm glad
tonight before you sleep
it's especially powerful before you
sleep just before you sleep just before
you fall asleep you think of all the
good things you did today rather than
worrying about your life what someone
said to you your finances blah blah blah
just before you fall asleep you must
think of one good thing you did today
and then that that cooks in your mind
all night and it's water on the sea and
that's based on a tantric personal
principle called
lonesome chupa-chupa which means where
the mind goes the prana follows so prana
will go to that scene if you think about
the scene and then it heats it up
psychically and it opens faster so what
I returns question is how can you do a
double meditation at night by accident
you see I name
which is a challenging question yeah I
mean if you want to see to be really
powerful like okay I gave money to a
homeless person today at the end of the
day you could think oh I gave money to a
homeless person you're supposed to
picture them in your mind you're
supposed to picture the money you gave
you're supposed to picture the look on
their face when you get my fried dog
girl and that's a that's a good end of
the day meditation you have put water on
your karmic scene okay but it's more
powerful okay if you reflect on the fact
that the money you gave them was created
by giving to people in the past you are
just passing it on you see it I mean you
don't own that money you didn't earn
that money well you did but but you you
you helped someone in the past and then
the money came to you you see so if you
want the meditation at the end of the
day to be more powerful you can think
about where did the money come from that
I gave to them it came because I gave
money in the past so is it a big
sacrifice to give the money to somebody
else
no because you're gonna give $50 back
okay like that so you can do an ignorant
end of the day meditation it's possible
oh I earned that money you know and I
sacrificed it that's an ignorant happy
meditation at the end of the day and
it's actually supporting the devil okay
so how do I do a non ignorant end of the
day meditation yeah I gave the money to
the other person which I got because I
gave money to the person before that I'm
just reinvesting you know I'm gonna get
more you know then that kind of thinking
is an enlightened end of the day
meditation okay so yeah to think I gave
away money that I work so hard for is is
a mistaken end of the day good
meditation
okay got it
there's your example Ironton and you if
I don't see you on the wheat what's up
tomorrow you're in trouble okay
okay so I see some of you guys at that
mountain and in any case I propose we
try to do this once a month or every
other month because otherwise it'll take
70 years to finish we calculated it
yesterday so now that we have a nice
place thanks to our sponsors from China
mostly we have a beautiful place to have
classes I think it'd be nice to knock
out this text okay so let's make a let's
try to do it
[Applause]